Guide to the Doris Duke Audiovisual Collection, 1919-2012 and undated RL.10005
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Doris Duke audiovisual collection
1899-2012 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke, Doris
RL.10005
51 Linear Feet
Doris Duke was the only child of James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke, a founder of the American Tobacco Company and Duke Energy Company and a benefactor of Duke University, and Nanaline Holt Duke. Although Doris did her best to live a private life, she carried on the Duke family's pattern of philanthropy by contributing to a number of public causes such as the arts, historic preservation, and the environment. Doris Duke died in October 1993 at the age of 80. In her will she left the majority of her estate to the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation. The Doris Duke Audio Visual Collection was created by combining 8mm, 16mm, and 35mm film reels, vinyl recordings, audiocassettes, and associated manuscript materials relating to Doris Duke's travels, her various estates, and her interests in jazz and gospel music, dance, history, and culture. The collection covers the years 1899 to 2012 and is organized into three series: Moving Images, Audio, and Sheet Music and Index Cards.
Biographical note
Born on November 22, 1912, Doris Duke was the only child of James Buchanan (J.B.) Duke, a founder of the American Tobacco Company and Duke Energy Company and a benefactor of Duke University, and Nanaline Holt Duke. Inheriting a bulk of her father's estate in 1925, which included Duke Farms in New Jersey, Rough Point in Newport, R.I., and a mansion in New York City, Doris was soon dubbed by the press as "the richest girl in the world." Although Doris did her best to live a private life, she carried on the Duke family's pattern of philanthropy by contributing to a number of public causes such as the arts, historic preservation, and the environment. Doris Duke died in October 1993 at the age of 80. In her will she left the majority of her estate to the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Digital use copies in this collection have been migrated to a library server and can only be accessed onsite in the Rubenstein Library Reading Room. To request access please contact Research Services prior to visiting the library.
Collection Overview
The Doris Duke Audiovisual Collection was created by combining 8mm, 16mm, and 35mm film reels, vinyl recordings, audiocassettes, and associated manuscript materials relating to Doris Duke's travels, her various estates, and her interests in jazz and gospel music, dance, history, and culture. The collection covers the years 1899 to 2012 and is organized into three series: Moving Images, Audio, and Sheet Music and Index Cards.
Provenance
The Doris Duke Audiovisual Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a donation from the Doris Duke Charitable Foundation in June 2009.
Related Materials
Doris Duke papers, 1798-2003 (bulk 1930-1999)
Doris Duke papers on the Duke Farms residence, 1859-2004 and undated
Doris Duke papers on the Shangri La residence, 1932-2003
Doris Duke Photograph Collection, 1870-2006
Duke Gardens Foundation records, 1912-2002
Home movies; Audiocassettes; Audiovisual materials; 8mm (photographic film size); 35mm; 16mm; Moving images; Cromwell, James H. R. (James Henry Roberts); Duke, James Buchanan, 1856-1925; Duke, Nanaline Holt Inman; Duke, Doris
- Moving Images, 1899-2012 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  The Moving Images series contains a compelling array of topics that reflect Doris Duke's wide and varied interests and pursuits. Main themes include travel, social events, life at her various residences, and documentation of historical events. Materials include films, VHS tapes, and DVDs. The series is further arranged into two subseries.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Digital copies of moving images are indicated by a Digital Materials designation. While many of the moving images in the Doris Duke Audiovisual collection have been digitized, those that have not require digitization prior to access. Please contact Rubenstein Library Research Services for further information.
  - Film, 1919-2012; 220 items
    Arrangement
    The materials in this subseries are arranged chronologically.
    This subseries contains 8mm, 16mm, and 35mm film reels and include an array of topics that reflect Doris' wide and varied interests and pursuits. The main themes in this subseries include travel, social events, life at her various residences, and documentation of historical events. Doris Duke travelled widely and the subseries includes footage of her trips to the Middle East, Morocco, and Europe. Also included is footage of the construction of Shangri La and visits to both Duke Farms and Rough Point at various times of her life. Doris' interest in and financial support of the performing arts is reflected in several films in the series including custom original prints of Egyptian dancer Nadia Gamal and Lebanese dancers (as part of the creation of the Near East Foundation) and extensive raw footage of Tahiti as part of her funding of jazz artist Syd Shaw's East West New Sounds production company. Of particular interest are the four 35mm negative nitrate reels of The Nazi Supreme Court Trial of the Anti-Hitler Plot from September 1944 to January 1945 which were likely given to Doris Duke when she was a war correspondent during the World War II.
    - Somerville Scenes, circa 1919 (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0003, Video-file RL10005-F35-0005_uc.mp4)
      Tinted. Roll #5 and #6 of Somerville Scenes. Includes scenes of young Doris Duke feeding swans, in boat, canoe. Scenes around Duke Farms. Man with pony (Princie Shep?) performing tricks. Also includes Doris Duke walking among rose trellis, holding a barrel, walking around, under, in tree and finally sitting on stone with small black dog.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 35mm print, 600 film feet (Box 44, Film-reel RL10005-F35-0005)
    - I Know a Garden (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0003, Video-file RL10005-F35-0012_uc.mp4)
      "I Know a Garden: Duke's Farms, Somerville, NJ" Presented by Prizma, photographed by Wm. T. Crespinal, arranged by Howard R. LeRoy. Opening view of bridge over Lake 45 from under grotto waterfalls. Surrey drawn by horses pulls up under bridge, travels around fountain, close-up of young Doris Duke sitting in surrey. JB and Nanaline Duke close-up, Doris Duke enters frame, they all walk near lake. Close-ups of two unidentified men, JB, Nanaline, and Doris walk around gardens, close-up of flowers, etc.
      - Original 35mm nitrate color composite print (Film-reel 13, Film-reel RL10005-F35-0009)
      - 35mm color internegative (Box 42, Film-reel RL10005-F35-0015)
      - 35mm preservation color composite print (Box 42, Film-reel RL10005-F35-0012)
    - DD 9, 10, 11, 12, 13, circa 1920s; 1950s (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0002, Video-file RL10005-F16-0012_uc.mp4)
      Comprised of footage shot in the 1920s and the 1950s. Footage from the 1920s is "I Know a Garden: Duke's Farms, Somerville, NJ" Presented by Prizma, photographed by Wm. T. Crespinal, arranged by Howard R. LeRoy. Opening view of bridge over Lake 45 from under grotto waterfalls. Surrey drawn by horses pulls up under bridge, travels around fountain, close-up of young Doris Duke sitting in surrey. JB&Nanaline Duke close-up, Doris Duke enters frame, they all walk near lake. Close-ups of two unidentified men, JB, Nanaline, and Doris walk around gardens, close-up of flowers, etc. Footage from the 1920s also includes young Doris Duke in white dress walking around grounds at Rough Point. She puts on hat, walks with companions in gardent, etc. Footage from the 1950s was shot in color and includes views of house, landscape, lakes, swans, deer, dogs at Duke Farms. Doris Duke and unidentified kids picking fruit from a tree.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., col., bw reversal print, 1050 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0012)
    - St. Patrick's, King of Siam, etc., circa 1920s-1930s (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0003, Video-file RL10005-F16-0022_uc.mp4)
      Various scenes throughout film, including the King of Siam (Prajadhipok), and his family visiting unknown locations (possibly Europe?). An assortment of indivduals are included in the scenes, presumably escorting the King as he tours. Also includes religious ceremony at St. Patrick's, although location is unknown. Final scenes are at a racetrack.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 450 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0022)
    - 14, ["Somerville Scenes - Mr.&Mrs. Duke"], 1922-1925
      Part of film is blue tint, other part is brown and orange tint. Opening shots of Coach Barn, includes on "Doris" boat on lake, fountains, carriage. Tour of the estate - looks like shot from a moving vehicle. Doris blowing kisses. Mr. Duke with unknown young woman. Last scenes are men working on fountain and road.
      - Original 35mm Print, 771 film feet (Film-reel 8, Film-reel RL10005-F35-0008)
    - Two Stones with One Bird, Part I, Kodascope Libraries Inc., 1923
      From the Collier's Weekly Stories by H.C. Witwer with George O'Hara, Clara Horton&All Star Cast. Fighting Blood Round 4, Part I.
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 400 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0030)
    - Two Stones with One Bird, Part II, Kodascope Libraries Inc., 1923
      From the Collier's Weekly Stories by H.C. Witwer with George O'Hara, Clara Horton&All Star Cast. Fighting Blood Round 4, Part II.
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 400 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0031)
    - Pathe' Review #9, 1924
      Stories on reel include: Bermuda Days: A Pictorial Study in and around Hamilton Harbor, Bermuda; Head and Heels: Something new in Aerial Trapeze Daring, as done by Enos Frazere; Petal Painting: Leonardo da Vinci: art school...New York City; The Canyon Country: In and Around the Grand Canyon
      - Original 35mm Print, 1000 film feet (Film-reel 6, Film-reel RL10005-F35-0006)
    - Kodak Cinegraph presents Airplane Acrobatics (Film No. 1548), circa 1926 (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0003, Video-file RL10005-F16-0035)
      Footage of airplane performing acrobatics.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., tinted reversal print, 125 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0035)
    - Horseshow, Riding, circa 1926-1929
      All of film is of horseshow, riding, and an assortment of unknown individuals attending and enjoying the event.
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 300 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0023)
    - Princeton, circa 1926-1929
      Most of film is unknown people at a graduation ceremony at Princeton University. Other scenes include riding in the country, a man riding a horse in the countryside, a Zeppelin in a hangar, and two unknown men in polo outfits.
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 500 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0025)
    - Day after, Reno, circa 1927
      Unknown woman and man making drinks at a bar and lighting cigarettes. Group of unknown women sitting on a hood of a car, riding horses presumably in or around Reno, NV
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 350 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0024)
    - Aviation - Reno, circa 1927
      Begins with street scenes in a downtown area (Reno?) with unknown people. Majority of the film is unknown woman and man preparing and then getting onto a bi-plane which presumably flies over Reno, NV. Includes aerial shots of Reno (someone filmed while a passenger) and shots of airplane in the air.
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 350 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0026)
    - Flood - Reno, circa 1927 (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0003, Video-file RL10005-F16-0027_uc.mp4)
      Documentation of 1927 flood of Reno, Nevada. Scenes including raging waters, views with flood survivors waiting out the flood, and people looking at the flood damage.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 150 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0027)
    - Kodak Cinegraph presents An Aerial Trip Over New York (Film No. 1512), circa 1927 (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0003, Video-file RL10005-F16-0029_uc.mp4)
      Includes aerial scenes of the Island of Manhattan, the Skyline from the Hudson River, the Harbor, Battery Park and the Aquarium, and the Statue of Liberty. All scenes are titled.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 100 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0029)
    - Unknown Rollerskate, 1920s-1930s, circa 1927
      Various scenes throughout film, including unknown man and two women walking around a city, and an unknown couple roller skating.
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 300 film feet (Box 5, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0033)
    - Bethlehem and Gethsemane, No. 1536, 1929
      A tour through Palestine in the 1920s, including many historical biblical sites.
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 100 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0056)
    - Pistol&Polo Practice, circa 1929
      Unknown young men practice shooting a target nailed to a tree. Other scenes include unknown man playing with a dog (the man has a black armband) and spectators and riders at a polo practice.
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 350 film feet (Box 4, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0028)
    - DD 1, 2, 3, 1929-1930s (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0002, Video-file RL10005-F16-0015_uc.mp4)
      Footage shot primarily at Duke Farms and Rough Point. Doris Duke and dogs walking through Duke Farms, landscape views, lakes, main residence, and fountains. Footage of inventory of items purchased on honeymoon; both James Cromwell and Doris Duke are looking at the items. Doris Duke, Marian Paschal, and unidentified people in antique cars drive around estate. Teenage Doris Duke and Nanaline Duke with unidentified companions, interior and exterior views of Rough Point. Doris Duke plays with airedale and dances with friend. Brief footage of a parade, spectators in Washington, DC. Planes and Zeppelin fly overhead.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., col., bw reversal print, 1000 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0015)
    - Thomas Edison Scholarship Contest 1930 (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0003, Video-file RL10005-F16-0034_uc.mp4)
      Fifty boys gather to compete for the 1930 Edison Scholarship. Arthur O. Williams from Providence, Rhode Island won the contest. Film includes several close ups of Thomas Edison.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 200 film feet (Box 2, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0034)
    - Doris Duke and Phillip Terry Screen Test (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0003, Video-file RL10005-F35-0013_uc.mp4)
      - Original 35mm b&w nitrate composite print (Film-reel 12, Film-reel RL10005-F35-0007)
      - 35mm b&w dupe negative (Box 42, Film-reel RL10005-F35-0014)
      - 35mm preservation b&w composite print (Box 1, Film-reel RL10005-F35-0013)
    - DD 51, circa 1930s (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0001, Video-file RL10005-F16-0002_uc.mp4)
      Various Hawaiian scenes. Initial view of palm trees. Also includes underwater shots (plants, people swimming), beach scenes, and ends with Hawaiian dancers.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 900 film feet (Box 6, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0002)
    - [Hindendburg Disaster], circa 1930s
      Film of the Hindenburg disaster on May 6, 1937. Titles are throughout, however it appears that the beginning of the film has been cut out, so the producer of the film is unknown.
      - Original 16mm, si., bw reversal print, 100 film feet (Box 6, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0055)
    - Of Men&Money, circa 1930s
      A film documentary from the book "In Defense of Capitalism" by James H.R. Cromwell and Hugo E. Czerkwonky. Print A.
      - Original 35mm Print, 2040 film feet (Film-reel 10, Film-reel RL10005-F35-0010)
    - Print A, circa 1930s
      A film documentary from the book "In Defense of Capitalism" by James H.R. Cromwell and Hugo E. Czerkwonky. Print B.
      - Original 35mm Print, 2040 film feet (Film-reel 11, Film-reel RL10005-F35-0011)
    - DD 47-50, circa late 1930s (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0001, Video-file RL10005-F16-0003_uc.mp4)
      Opens with a large outdoor dinner party with Doris Duke, James Cromwell and others in Palm Springs. Southern California mountain scenery, Doris Duke swimming in pool, unidentified people on bikes. Flim transitions to Doris Duke, James Cromwell and company in shooting party in mountainous landscape of Scotland. Doris, James, and Marian Paschal also walk around castle grounds and other parts of Scotland. Next scene of film opens with a view of the Stotesburys' Whitemarsh Hall mansion in Wyndmoor, Pennsylvania. Unidentified people at outdoor reception, however several shots includes Edward and Eva Stotesbury. Doris Duke not evident. Last part of film is in Palm Beach and includes James Cromwell and older woman (Eva Stotesbury[?]) walking around estate, Cromwell shows off beach and himself, etc. Also includes Doris and a group of people eating a meal outdoors. Doris clowns around with unknown couple at the end of the film.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., col. reversal print, 1000 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0003)
    - DD 34, circa late 1930s (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0001, Video-file RL10005-F16-0007_uc.mp4)
      Doris Duke, James Cromwell, Sam Kahanamoku and others fishing off boat, Doris Duke and others riding horses, external shots of Shangri La (including close ups of playhouse), some construction of Shangri La. Also includes aerial views of the islands and shots of a variety of activities around the island with Doris, James Cromwell, Marian Paschal, and members of the Kahanamoku family.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., col. reversal print, 1200 film feet (Box 3, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0007)
    - DD 35, circa late 1930s (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0002, Video-file RL10005-F16-0008_uc.mp4)
      Appears to be a continuation of RL10005-F16-0007. Primarliy shots of Doris Duke and James Cromwell and others sailing and fishing off boat, construction of Shangri La. Also includes brief shots of Doris playing with a bird and James Cromwell showing an unknown couple Shangri La's construction site. Last shot is Doris and James leaving the islands on a seaplane.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., col. reversal print, 500 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0008)
    - DD 19, 20, 24, circa late 1930s (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0002, Video-file RL10005-F16-0011_uc.mp4)
      Filmed in Hawaii. Includes views of boat underway near Diamond Head and Doris Duke on beach with Kahanamokus and other companions for a cookout. Also has shots of Christine Cromwell[?] riding a horse, Doris Duke inspecting the construction of Shangri La with H. Drewry Baker, Johnny Gomez diving, Rabbit Island near Oahu, and aerial shots of Hawaiian volcano.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., col. reversal print, 1000 film feet (Box 5, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0011)
    - Slow Motion Analysis of Bobby Jones No. 1567, 1931 (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0003, Video-file RL10005-F16-0036_uc.mp4)
      Film commissioned by the PGA in 1930. Bobby Jones was a well known amateur golfer.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., tinted reversal print, 300 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0036)
    - DD 16, 17, 18, 1936-1937 (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0002, Video-file RL10005-F16-0010_uc.mp4)
      Most of film in Hawaii. Includes Kahanamokus, hula dancer, Marion Sims Wyeth and James Cromwell, with title cards, e.g., "February in Hawaii 1937"; "Now now Mr. Cromwell, that's not in my contract". Also includes construction of Shangri La, Kahanamokus et al, playing around on beach, Doris Duke and James Cromwell on a passenger ship showing off their leis, scenery, Marian Paschal in a canoe, and Doris Duke, James Cromwell and companions traveling to Hawaiian volcano.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., col., bw reversal print, 1200 film feet (Box 4, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0010)
    - DD 7, 8, 1937; 1956 (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0002, Video-file RL10005-F16-0013_uc.mp4)
      Comprised of footage shot at Duke Farms in the fall of 1956 and Somerville and Newport in 1937. 1956 footage includes Joey Castro sitting in back seat of a convertible with dogs, Doris Duke at the steering wheel. General scenic views of Duke Farms. 1937 footage is Doris Duke with companions at a polo match, and scenic views of Rough Point and the ocean.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., col. reversal print, 800 film feet (Box 1, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0013)
    - DD 37-39, 1937-1938 (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0001, Video-file RL10005-F16-0001_uc.mp4)
      Doris Duke and companions, Moroccan people in towns, airplanes, scenic views, etc. Various scenic views of towns and cities in Germany and Austria. Also includes footage from 1938 trip to the Middle East primarily camel races and some brief shots of Palmyra and Aleppo.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., col., bw reversal print, 1100 film feet (Box 3, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0001)
    - DD 40&41, circa 1938 (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0001, Video-file RL10005-F16-0005_uc.mp4)
      Documents Doris Duke's trip to the Middle East. Includes shots of Doris Duke and companions (Mary Crane and Marian Paschal?) near ruins, watching men perform card tricks, views of towns and plaza with horses, unidentified people arriving in carriages. Views of architectural and design details; walls, tile floors, etc. in various Middle Eastern cities.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, si., col. reversal print, 650 film feet (Box 5, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0005)
    - [Untitled], circa 1939
      Sound reference film to calibrate sound. "Use the title of this practice strip as a test for focus and the sound track for testing sound reproduction".
      - Original 16mm, sd., bw reversal print, 75 film feet (Box 5, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0039)
    - Phantom Empire, circa 1939 (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0003, Video-file RL10005-F16-0040_uc.mp4)
      James Cromwell is in an office, sitting at desk. He speaks about he recent appointment as Minister to Canada and the close relationship between the United States and Canada. Then speaks about how the war could impact this relationship.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room
      - Original 16mm, sd., bw reversal print, 75 film feet (Box 5, Film-reel RL10005-F16-0040)
    - W. Choi Shangri La, circa early 1940s (Digital-materials RL10005-SET-0001, Video-file RL10005-F8-0001_uc.mp4)
      Film "postcard" from W. Choi at Shangri La to Doris Duke (via Marian Paschal to whom the film was mailed). Shows various scenes of the estate particularly focusing on flowers in bloom around the pool, driveway, and the playhouse.Digital use copy is available in the Reading Room